another technique that uses a similar
idea to what we did when we increased
the block size to reduce the number of
Misses is called prefetching the way
prefetching works is that we guess which
blocks will be accessed soon in the
future before they're actually accessed
and then we bring those blocks into the
cache ahead of time before they actually
will be accessed so with no prefetching
if time goes to the right we might have
an axis here let's say load Word a and
then we check
quickly whether it's in our cache and if
it is not we will go to memory and spend
a lot of time waiting for it until it
comes back so here we can supply the
data to the processor so this is what
happens with no prefetching with
prefetching assuming that the load would
happen here sometime before the load we
have to guess that a will be accessed
and request it from memory now what was
memory latency here will be here and at
this point the block is in the cache so
when we try to load it we have a hit so
as you can see with prefetching we're
guessing what will be accessed and start
fetching it from memory into the cache
if we guess correctly instead of a Miss
we get a hit if we guess
incorrectly we brought something into
the cache that replaced something that
might have been useful so with
prefetching we have that good guesses
will eliminate misses but bad guesses
lead to what is called Cash pollution
because we're bringing stuff that is
useless into the cash if it doesn't get
access that means that maybe it would
never have been brought into the cash in
the first place and because of cash
pollution because we kick out something
that might have been useful with useless
data not
only that we didn't eliminate the Miss
here because we guessed wrongly we also
might have created another Miss because
we kicked out something that later might
be accessed and that we don't like so
overall prefetching is about trying to
make good guesses so that we eliminate
misses while trying to eliminate bad
guesses because we don't want to create
additional misses